A Guide to the Anne Virginia Agnew Papers, 1919-1943
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Anne Virginia Agnew Papers, 1919-1943
Library of Virginia
42287
1.05 cu. ft. and 1 oversize folder
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Helen Wolfe Evans, Raleigh, North Carolina, 31 October 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
Anne Virginia Agnew, known as "Jean," was born in Nottoway County, Virginia, on 5 December 1872, the tenth child of Dr. James Anderson Agnew (1828-1879) and Martha Chaffin Scott Agnew (1832-1872). With their mother's death the day after Jean's birth, some of the eight surviving children were sent to live elsewhere. Jean was placed with Richard Anderson Miller (1840-1919) and his wife Sarah Elizabeth Crowder Miller (1844-1926), relatives of the Agnews. The Millers later had two children of their own, Richard (1874-1940) and Mary (1877-1926 or 7). The family lived first at Stone Knoll, a house in Prince Edward County, Virginia, and then at Grape Lawn, near Burkeville, Nottoway County, Virginia. Throughout her life, Jean also maintained close relationships with her natural siblings.
Born deaf, Jean Agnew learned to read lips, and communicated with her family through sign language. She worked as a teacher in several schools for the deaf, some of which she helped to establish. In later years, she supported herself by working as a genealogist, and was credited for her insistence on accuracy and citation. At the encouragement of sister Ella Graham Agnew (1871-1958), she eventually took up residence in the Home for Needy Confederate Women in Richmond, Virginia. She died in 1944 after being hit by a train. Some in the family believed that her death may have been a suicide, as she had feared that an upcoming cataracts surgery would leave her blind and completely dependent on the help of others.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1919-1943, of and pertaining to genealogist Anne Virginia "Jean" Agnew (1872-1944), are largely comprised of notes she gathered while researching her own ancestry and that of her clients. Some of the surnames researched include Archer, Baldwin, Chaffin, Claiborne, Cox, Flippin or Flippen, Hobson, Hughes, Jones, Miller, Scott, Ward, and Webb. For a more detailed listing of families mentioned in the files, see the folder listing. At times, notes are supplemented by newspaper clippings and photographs. Two collections of family anecdotes, Agnew's Our Vine and Figtree and Some Family Incidents, and the booklet Graham Scott's Letter to his Nephew and Namesake, also offer insight into whites' attitudes toward African Americans in mid- 19th to early 20th-century Virginia. Other items include Agnew's genealogy "work book"; a handful of scholarly and genealogical journals; and four letters, dated 1919-1943, in which Agnew gives general updates on her life and the goings-on of family members, including sister Ella Graham Agnew (1871-1958).
Arrangement
File names and groupings assigned by Anne Virginia Agnew have for the most part been maintained. In some cases, information on several families was kept within a single file; the groupings do not necessarily indicate relationships between the families.
Contents List
- Papers, 1919-1943 (Box 1)
  Papers, 1919-1988, of and pertaining to genealogist Anne Virginia "Jean" Agnew (1872-1944), are largely comprised of notes she gathered while researching her own ancestry and that of her clients. Some of the surnames include Archer, Baldwin, Chaffin, Claiborne, Cox, Flippin or Flippen, Hobson, Hughes, Jones, Miller, Scott, Ward, and Webb. For a more detailed listing of families mentioned in the files, see the folder listing in the finding aid. At times, notes are supplemented by newspaper clippings and photographs. Two collections of family anecdotes, Agnew's "Our Vine and Figtree and Some Family Incidents," and the booklet "Graham Scott's Letter to his Nephew and Namesake," also offer insight into whites' attitudes toward African Americans in mid-19th to early 20th-century Virginia. Other items include Agnew's so-called genealogy "work book"; a handful of scholarly and genealogical journals; and four letters, dated 1919-1943, in which Agnew gives general updates on her life and the goings-on of family members, including sister Ella Graham Agnew (1871-1958).
  File names and groupings assigned by Anne Virginia Agnew have for the most part been retained. In some cases, information on several families was kept within a single file; the groupings do not necessarily indicate relationships between the families.
  - Agnew (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Agnew, J. Stuart (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Amelia County (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Amelia County records (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anderson (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Archer-Osborne-Hughes (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Armistead-Wills-Pryor-Newman (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baldwin (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bedford County wills (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bookers and Jeters, Amelia County (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bowdoin-Robins (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bradley-Lyon (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Branch (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cary (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Childrey, Jackson Frayser (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chiles-Cheadle (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Claiborne (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Crawley (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dabney (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Daniel-Cunningham-Watkins-Worsham (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Deardons of Prince George County (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dryden-Gale-McClure-Lessley (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Eltonhead-Conway-Thacker-Hickman-Greenhill (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Eppes (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Farley (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Fitzgerald (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Fletchers of Brunswick and Nottoway Co. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Flippin-Flippen-Walton-Cox-LeGrand-Hobson-Brown (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Fowlkes-Jennings (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Genealogy work book (Box 1, Folder 32-34)
  - Giles-Graham-Page (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Gordon (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Graham Scott's Letter to His Nephew and Namesake, Graham Scott II (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Hanover records (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Henrico County (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Henrico Parish, in the Diocese of Virginia, and the Parishes Descended Therefrom (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - History of Richmond (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Hughes of Hughes Creek and Muddy Creek (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Huguenot history (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Jones (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Jones-Fitzgerald-Epes (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Leigh (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Letters, 1919-1943 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Louisa County Records (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Magazines and journals (Box 49-52)
  - Merryman (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Miller (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Miller-Agnew (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Miller-Agnew-Baldwin-Scott (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Miller-Anderson-Dabney (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Miller-Carter-Heath-Barbee-Daniel-Thacker (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Morgan-Wilson-Willson-Scott-Osborne (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Mosby (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Neale-Marshall (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Notes from Richmond Enquirer, 1815 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Notes from Vestry Book of St. Paul's Parish, 1705-1781, Hanover County (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Notes on Southside, Va., extracts (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Nottoway County order books, 1790's (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Nottoway County session book, 1837-1890 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Our Vine and Figtree, and Some Family Incidents (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Perkinson wills, Amelia County (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Peters (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Pettus (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Photostats of churches (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Powhatan County archives (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Preston (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Price (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Prince Edward County marriage bonds, 1785-1857 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Prince Edward County marriages (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Prince George County deeds (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Scott Bible photostats (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Scott-Chaffin (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Scott (lateral) (Box 3, Folder 81-82)
  - Spencer (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Tanner-Hatcher (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Taylor (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Ward (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Ward-Ammon (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Webb (Box 3, Folder 88-89)
  - Webb, Mrs. Anne Darden--Ancestry of (Box 3, Folder 90-91)
  - Wythe County wills (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Young (Box 3, Folder 93)